Guide to the Monarch Lumber Company records 1914-1961
Montana Historical Society Research Center
Monarch Lumber Company records
1914-1961
Montana Historical Society, Research Center Archives Archives 225 N. Roberts PO Box 201201 Helena MT 59620-1201 (406) 444-2681 mhslibrary@mt.gov
MC 213
Monarch Lumber Company.
1 linear foot of shelf space
The Libby Lumber Company was a retail lumber business in Libby, Montana. In 1916 it was sold to the Libby Yards Company, which in turn was sold to the Monarch Lumber Company of Great Falls in 1921 and to Building Service, Inc. in 1933. Under all four names the business conducted a state-wide retail lumber and real estate trade. Records (1914-1961) are arranged into subgroups for the different companies and include general correspondence, court papers, financial records, legal documents, minutes, organizational materials, reports, and miscellany.
Historical Note:
Libby Lumber Company, with home offices in Minneapolis, Minnesota, had its principal place of business in Libby, Montana. The firm was incorporated as a retail outlet. In 1916 Libby Lumber Company sold its property to Libby Yards Company which was incorporated to sell merchandise, property, and real estate,, and to operate a general manufacturing and contracting business. Libby Yards had retail operations in many Montana communities including Madoc, East Scobey, Antelope, Froid, Plentywood, Gilman, Great Falls, Kevin, Beaverton, Scobey, Shelby, Brady, Big Sandy, Conrad, Valier, Redstone, Sunburst, Cut Bank, Glendive, Homestead, and Saco.
In 1921 Monarch Lumber Company took over the preferred stock of Libby Yards Company. Monarch Lumber Company was incorporated in the state of Delaware listing its principal place of business in Great Falls, Montana. The first meeting of the company's board of directors was held in 1921 in Minneapolis.
Building Service, Inc. was formed in 1933 at the first meeting of its board of directors in Great Falls. At that meeting it was determined that Building Service, Inc. would purchase stock "now owned or controlled by the Monarch Lumber Company and used in the conduct of its wholesale business," thus becoming the wholesale outlet for Monarch Lumber Company. The main warehouse for Building Service, Inc. was in Great Falls. Employees for the company included Russell (Ben) Wallace, manager; G.H. Rogers and P.V. Eames, presidents in the Minneapolis office; Roy Forney and Gordon F. Mick, managers of the Billings branch warehouse; and F.D. Wilson, assistant treasurer in Great Falls. Building Service, Inc. was liquidated in 1961 when the company sold all its assets to the Boise Cascade Corporation.
This collection is arranged in three subgroups. The Libby Lumber Company/Libby Yards Company subgroup contains general correspondence (1917-1921); court papers (1923-1924); financial records (1914-1936); and legal documents (1922-1934).
The Monarch Lumber Company subgroup includes general correspondence (1921-1961); court papers (1925-1930); financial records (1928-1961); legal documents (1923-1958); minutes (1921-1936) for board of directors, executive committee, and stockholders meetings; organizational materials (1921-1923); reports (1922-1936); and miscellany.
The Building Service, Inc. subgroup includes general correspondence (1937-1961); financial records (1933-1960) including annual reports and taxes; legal documents (1916-1961); minutes (1933-1961) of board of directors and stockholders meetings; organizational materials (1933-1961); reports (1935-1959); and miscellany.
by subgroup and series
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Lumber trade--Montana--Libby
Lumber trade--Montana--Great Falls
Real estate business--Montana.
Great Falls (Mont.)--Commerce
Libby (Mont.)--Commerce
Montana
Forestry and Forestry Products
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Libby Lumber Company / Libby Yards Company
  - General Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous, 1917-1921, 1923-1924 (Box-folder 1 / 1-2)
  - Financial Records
    - Miscellaneous, 1914-1936 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - Legal Documents
    - Agreements, contracts, liens, and mortgages, 1915-1925 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
- Monarch Lumber Company
  - General Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous, 1921-1961 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
  - Court Papers
    - Miscellaneous, 1925-1930 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - Financial Records
    - Insurance for employees (lists employees and age), 1928-1938 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
    - Insurance policies, 1959-1961 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
    - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - Legal Documents
    - Abstract, agreements, contract, mortgages (includes agreements re Gibbons-Dempsey boxing match), 1922-1934 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
    - Liens, 1923-1958 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
  - Minutes
    - Board of director's meetings, 1922-1936 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
    - Executive committee meetings, 1921-1936 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
    - Stockholders' meetings, 1922-1936 (Box-folder 1 / 14)
  - Organization
    - Articles of incorporation; list of stockholders, 1921-1923 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
  - Reports
    - To directors from president, vice president, general manager, 1922-1936 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
  - Miscellany
    - Sketch of lots owned, n.d. (Box-folder 1 / 17)
- Building Service, Inc
  - General Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous, 1937-1951 (Box-folder 1 / 18)
    - Miscellaneous, 1952-1961 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
  - Financial Records
    - Annual reports; profit sharing statements; etc., 1933-1960 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
    - Taxes, 1934-1960 (Box-folder 2 / 3)
  - Legal Documents
    - Agreements, bills of sale, contracts, debentures, lease, liens, statements, etc. (includes transactions with Monarch Lumber Company, Midland Sash and Ddoor; also includes employee pension plan agreement), 1916-1961 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
  - Minutes
    - Board of director's meetings, 1933-1961 (Box-folder 2 / 5-6)
    - Stockholders' annual and special meetings, 1933-1961 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
  - Organization
    - Articles of incorporation; bylaws; lists of stockholders; resolutions, 1933-1961 (Box-folder 2 / 8)
  - Reports
    - Reports to directors and stockholders from the president, secretary, manager; report of building inspection, 1935-1944, 1959 (Box-folder 2 / 9)
  - Miscellany
    - Stock certificates for Economic Development Corporation of Great Falls; stock certificates and bylaws for Great Falls Employer's Council, 1946, 1960 (Box-folder 2 / 10)